So I know what you're thinking.
무슨 생각 하시는지 알아요
You're thinking, what's going on here?
무슨 일인가 싶죠
We're on day five.
오늘이 5일째예요
We're on day five of week five.
5주 차 중 5일째예요
Why does he have a Jupyter notebook open?
왜 주피터 공책을 펼쳐놨죠?
That's called day 4.5.
4일째라고 하죠 5분
And it's because it's just a little quick deviation on day four to show you genuinely how straightforward
넷째 날에 잠깐 편차가 생겼기 때문이죠 벡터 데이터 저장소를 다른 것으로 바꾸는 게
it is to switch out the vector data store for another one.
얼마나 간단한지 보여드리려고요
And since this is super common out there, used a lot, I thought it was a great one to show you and
이건 아주 흔하고 많이 사용되니까 여러분께 보여드리기에 좋을 것 같았어요 다른 벡터 데이터
to use it both to illustrate a different vector data store, and also to show you how easy it is to
저장소를 표시하는 데 둘 다 사용하고 이런 추상화로 작업하는 게 얼마나 쉬운지도 보여드리기
work with these abstractions.
위해서요
Now, something to to explain is that this isn't really a vector data store.
설명해드릴 게 있는데 이건 벡터 데이터 저장소가 아니에요
It stands for Facebook AI Similarity Search, and it's a highly used, very common open source library
Facebook 인공지능 동시성 검색을 뜻합니다 페이스북이 만든 자주 사용되는 아주 일반적인 오픈
put out by Facebook that lets you do quick search for vectors close to other vectors, and as such,
소스 라이브러리예요 서로 가까운 벡터에 대한 빠른 검색을 가능하게 하죠 그래서 일종의
it is often used as a kind of in-memory vector store.
인 메모리 벡터 스토어로 사용돼요
It doesn't persist on the disk, but you can use it to plonk in vectors and to retrieve other vectors
디스크에 남아 있진 않지만 벡터를 불러오고 유사한 다른 벡터를 검색하기 위해
that are similar, and you can also just use it as a library to do similarity search, to be looking
사용할 수 있어요 라이브러리로도 사용할 수 있죠 유사한 검색을 하기
for vectors close to other vectors, and Langshan has the right abstractions built around it, so it
위해서요 다른 벡터에 가까운 벡터를 찾기 위해서요 랭샨은 그에 대해 올바른 추상화가 내장되어 있어요
can just be a drop in replacement for chroma.
그래서 크로마를 대체할 수 있죠
So we use chroma before, which was persistent on disk.
채도를 사용했는데 디스크에 영구적으로 남아 있었죠
So it's a more serious hardcore data store vice.
좀 더 심각한 데이터 스토어 악습이죠
We can just use that in lieu of chroma.
채도 대신 쓰면 돼요
And I'm going to show you how easy it is because the code is going to be almost identical, except when
얼마나 쉬운지 보여드릴게요 코드는 거의 동일할 테니까요 해당 추상화와
we get to that abstraction and a couple of other things.
몇 가지 다른 걸 제외하면요 get get it
So we run the imports as before in this import.
이 import에서 아까처럼 import를 실행하고요.
You can see I have commented out the import for chroma, so I can't cheat.
크로마에 불러오기를 주석으로 달아 놓은 게 보이시죠 커닝이 안 돼요
Chroma will not be included here and instead we're importing face Facebook AI similarity search.
크로마는 여기 포함되지 않습니다 대신 페이스 페이스북 인공지능 유사성 검색을 불러왔죠
It's worth noting that face comes in two variations a CPU variant and a GPU variant, depending on which
두 가지 변형이 있다는 걸 알아두세요 CPU 변형과 GPU 변형이죠 Pip가 설치된
you have Pip installed.
것에 따라서요
And with this environment, of course, I have Pip installed the CPU variant, but for high performance
이 환경에선 Pip가 CPU 변종을 설치했지만 GPU에서
projects running on GPU, you can run the GPU version to run at blazing speed, so we've imported vice
실행되는 고성능 프로젝트를 위해서는 엄청난 속도로 실행할 수 있습니다 바이스를 불러왔는데 에러가
and no errors, which is great.
없어요, 훌륭하죠
Set up some things.
몇 가지 준비해 주세요
This is all the same code.
모두 같은 코드예요
We load everything in as before.
전처럼 전부 실어요
We're going to get hopefully 123 uh, to change that to be Len chunks.
get 123개만 있으면 렌 덩어리로 바꿀 수 있어요
So we see do we have 123.
자, 123개가 나왔네요
Yes we do.
네, 맞아요
Let's check that we have the right metadata.
메타데이터가 맞는지 확인하죠
We have the four types.
네 가지 종류가 있어요
So far nothing is different.
지금까지는 달라진 게 없어요
This is all the same.
다 똑같아요
But look at this.
하지만 이걸 보세요
One line has changed here cunningly.
한 줄이 교묘하게 바뀌었어요
Uh, I didn't need to draw quite so much attention to it.
그렇게 주의를 끌 필요는 없었어요
I think you probably spotted it already.
이미 눈치챈 것 같은데요
So we used to say vector store is chroma dot from documents.
벡터 스토어는 크로마.문서로부터의 크로마.이죠
And we passed in the chunks embeddings and the persist directory.
덩크 삽입과 지속 디렉터리도 통과시켰죠
And now we just say vice dot from documents same construct.
이제 같은 구성체에서 bice.를 입력해요
We also pass in the chunks.
덩어리도 나눠줘요
We also pass in the embeddings.
삽입구도 통과시키죠
And of course we don't pass in a persist directory because vice doesn't persist on disk.
디렉터리에는 전달되지 않습니다 바이스가 디스크에 남지 않기 때문이죠
Um, now these two lines here are also different.
여기 이 두 선도 달라요
So the lower level ways to ask questions of the data store are different.
데이터 저장소에 질문을 하는 낮은 레벨의 방법은 달라요
So if you're going to be using Feist, it's useful to have this to hand so you know how you can query
Feist를 사용할 경우 이게 있으면 유용합니다 벡터의 수나 차원값
for things like the number of vectors and the dimensionality.
같은 것에 대해 쿼리를 할 수 있으니까요
I don't know if you remember how many dimensions that there were when we did this in chroma.
채도로 할 때 몇 개의 차원이 있었는지 기억하실지 모르겠네요
Um, but it's the same number of dimensions we're coming up with here.
하지만 여기 나오는 차원의 개수는 같아요
We're using the same OpenAI embeddings to vectorize.
같은 오픈AI 엠딩을 벡터라이즈로 사용하고 있어요
So we're still using the same LLM to create the vectors.
벡터를 생성하기 위해 동일한 LLM을 사용하고 있죠
The thing that has changed is how we are storing those vectors, not in chroma but in Feis.
바뀐 건 벡터들을 저장하는 방법이에요 크로마가 아니라 Feis에요
Um, and so uh, no surprise there 123 vectors, one for each chunk.
123마리의 벡터가 한 덩어리당 한 마리씩 있는 건 당연해요
And they have these dimensions coming back from OpenAI.
오픈라이에서 온 차원들이 있어요
Uh, so the other thing that's changed has been this pre-work section was different in day four.
또 바뀐 건 작업 전 섹션이 4일째에 달라졌다는 거예요
I'll remind you in day four, the pre-work.
4일째에 다시 알려드릴게요 사전 작업이죠
Let's go and take a look at that.
가서 한번 보죠
Uh, ba ba ba ba.
네, 네
Uh, the pre-work actually looks a bit simpler just plucking out the vectors, documents, and doc types
pre-work는 더 간단해 보입니다. 크로마에서 벡터, 문서, doc 타입을
from chroma.
가져오는 것이죠.
And you can look at the ways that you query chroma to get this data.
이 데이터를 get을 위해 채도 쿼리를 하는 방법도 볼 수 있죠
Um, and this is how I did it for vice.
풍기단속반에서 일할 때도 이렇게 했어요
There might be a tighter way to do that, but this seems simple enough.
더 빡빡한 방법이 있을 수도 있지만 이 정도면 간단해 보이네요
I just collect the same vectors, documents, doc types, colors, and I map it into the color that
문서, 문서 타입, 색깔 등 같은 벡터를 수집하고 예상되는 색상에 매핑합니다.
Plotly is expecting so that we can just plot the same, uh, diagram so we can visualize our vectors
다이어그램과 같은 방식으로 벡터를 시각화할 수 있습니다. 2D에서 했던
just as we did before in 2D.
것처럼요.
This code is identical with one tiny exception.
이 코드는 한 가지만 빼고 동일해요
See if you can spot it.
찾을 수 있나 보세요
That's the only change.
그게 유일한 변화죠
I've changed the title from saying chroma to saying vice, but otherwise the code is the same.
제목을 크로마에서바이스로 바꿨습니다 하지만 그 외 코드는 같아요
Uh, we will visualize our data store.
데이터 저장소를 시각화할 거예요
And so here then are the vectors as they are represented in vice.
여기 벡터가 있습니다 악행에서 묘사되는 모습이죠
And of course, as you would expect, it's the same vectorization approach.
물론 예상하셨겠지만 벡터화 접근법은 같아요
So it looks pretty similar.
그래서 비슷해 보이죠
We're just using a different underlying technology as our vector data store.
벡터 데이터 저장소로 다른 기본 기술을 사용할 뿐이죠
Uh, and we can of course represent that in 3D.
물론 3D로 표현할 수 있죠
And we're now looking at the 3D representation in vice and nice to see that actually this time we've
지금 바이스에서 3D 표현을 보고 있는데 아주 보기 좋네요 이번엔
got, it's uh nicely it's very nicely separated.
아주 잘 분리됐어요
There we go.
됐어요
Anyway, I could look at that all day.
온종일 볼 수도 있겠어요
So you get that sense.
Get it, get it, get it. 그런 느낌이죠
And then the code to bring it all together is identical.
그걸 한데 모으는 코드는 동일하고요
I haven't changed this at all.
하나도 안 바꿨어요
Vector stored as retriever can be called on chroma, or it can be called on face.
레트리버로 저장된 벡터는 채도로 호출되거나 얼굴로 호출될 수 있어요
And it is the same.
그게 그거죠
So there we go.
자, 됐어요
We run it.
우리가 운영해요
No errors.
오류는 없어요
It's fine.
괜찮아요
Let's go straight to bringing up Gradio.
바로 그라디오 얘기를 하죠
Uh, and here we go.
자, 시작할게요
Here is our Gradio interface.
이게 그라디오 인터페이스예요
Um, now, one of the things that I meant to show you last time that I now take this chance, and you
지난번에 보여드리려고 했던 것 중 하나가 채도 검사에서도 같은
can see the same will apply in chroma as well, is I can take questions like, uh, like you remember
효과를 볼 수 있어요 질문을 받을 수 있는데 에이버리가 전에
last time I asked, what did Avery do before?
뭘 했는지 기억하시죠
And it was cunning enough to look up the right context, even though I didn't say Lancaster and I spelled
올바른 컨텍스트를 검색할 만큼 교활합니다 랭커스터라고
it with a lowercase a, we can take that even further, and I can say something like, what did?
하지 않고 소문자 a로 썼는데도요 더 나아가서 이렇게 말할 수도 있죠
And I can spell Avery's name wrong like that.
에이버리 이름도 그렇게 틀리게 쓸 수 있어요
What did Avery do before?
에이버리는 뭘 했죠?
Um, uh.
네
And I can run this piece of code like it is and have a look at what's come back.
이 코드를 그대로 실행해 뭐가 나왔는지 보죠
It has correctly identified that I'm talking about Avery Lancaster, and it looked up her HR document
에이버리 랭커스터에 대해 정확히 식별했습니다 그녀의 인사 기록을 찾아봤고 이노베이트
and it's again correctly identified that she worked at Innovate Insurance Solutions.
보험 솔루션에서 일했다는 걸 다시 정확히 식별했어요
Uh, we can might as well go in and just quickly check.
들어가서 빨리 확인해 보죠
Since it's set, it will go to the employees documents.
이미 정해졌으니까 직원들 서류로 가야죠
We find Avery Lancaster.
에이버리 랭커스터를 찾았어요
Here it is.
여기 있네요
Here is her HR record.
인사 기록이에요
Let's see what she did.
어떻게 했는지 보죠
She was indeed at Innovate Insurance Solutions before founding insurer Elm.
이노베이트 보험 솔루션에서 일하긴 했죠 인큐어 엘름 창립 전에요
Uh, it's good to see it didn't invent that.
이게 발명품이 아니라 다행이네요
Uh, so, um, uh, the bottom line is that it's this this gives you a real sense that it didn't just
그러니까 요점은 이겁니다 이걸 보면 텍스트 매칭만 한 게 아니란 걸 알 수
do text matching.
있어요
It didn't even, uh, get fussed by the wrong case that it was in lowercase and uppercase.
심지어 잘못된 케이스로 비난받지도 않았어요 소문자나 대문자로요 get it get it
It actually was able to identify that Avery spelt wrong, has the same meaning as Avery spelt with a
철자가 틀렸다는 걸 밝혀냈어요 Y로 시작하는 랭커스터와 같은
Y Avery Lancaster.
의미라는 걸요
It has enough common sense to recognize that that is very plausibly what we were after.
상식적으로 충분히 우리가 추구하는 게 그거라는 걸 알 수 있죠
And again, the reason is because when it turned this into a vector and it put it in the vector and
왜냐하면 이것을 벡터로 바꿀 때 벡터로 놓았기 때문입니다. 벡터 데이터
it looked in the vector data store for the vectors that were close to that, it found the Avery Lancaster's
스토어에서 그것과 가까운 벡터를 보면 에이버리 랭커스터의 HR 기록이 데이터 스토어에서
HR record as being something that was close to that in the data store.
그것과 비슷한 것을 발견하게 되죠.
So I think it's fascinating to see that you can spell things wrong and it still works.
철자를 틀려도 잘 된다는 게 정말 놀라워요
And it's such a clear example of how much better using the vector lookup approach is than using the
벡터 찾기 접근법이 첫 번째 시간에 사용한 브루트 포스 기술보다 얼마나 나은지
brute force technique that we used in the first session, which obviously would have failed hopelessly
보여주는 명백한 예입니다 이 테스트에서는 가망이 전혀
with this test.
없었겠죠
So I will let you prove to yourself that the same test will work if you use chroma, of course, and
채도를 사용하면 같은 결과가 나온다는 걸 증명하게 해 드릴게요 둘 다 해 볼
you can try out both, but you will see.
수 있지만 두고 보세요
I hope that chroma and vice have both worked very well indeed.
채도와 바이스가 잘 맞았으면 좋겠네요
But most importantly, you've seen that.
하지만 가장 중요한 건 그걸 봤다는 거예요
True to what I explained before, Lang makes it super simple to switch out different vector data stores
전에 설명드린 대로 랭은 아주 간단하게 뒤에서 다른 벡터 데이터 저장소를 변경하게 합니다
behind the scenes and use the same plumbing for your Rag workflow.
래그 워크플로우에도 같은 배관을 사용하고요
All right, back to the slides.
슬라이드로 돌아가죠